所以你可能会想
so you might think
我们的要求
our request
我们之前产生的处理过程
handling process that we spawned previously
是唯一在铀中运行的过程
is the only process running in the uranium
但事实证明，elixir 应用程序是由一个
but it turns out that elixir apps are made up of a
很多流程
lot of processes
实际上
in fact
让我们看看当前有多少进程正在运行
let's see how many processes are currently running
是的，我会启动一个 ix 会话
yeah to do that I'll fire up an ix session
正如我们在上一个视频中看到的
and as we saw in the previous video
Elixir 有一个流程模块
elixir has a process module
我们可以调用一个列表函数
and we can call a list function
哇，有很多过程
wow that's a lot of processes
我们看到所有那些孩子
we see all those kids
这是一个孩子的名单 事实上有一个
and it's a list of kids and in fact there's a
dot dot 表示还有更多这些
dot dot meaning there's a bunch more of these
所以让我们拿这个，我们将它输送到酶计数中
so let's take this and we'll pipe it into enzyme count
哇，目前有 83 个进程正在运行
and wow there's 83 processes currently running
那么这些进程在做什么
so what are these processes doing
很好地发现我们可以使用这个称为观察者的工具
well to find out we could use this tool called observer
它是早期的模块观察者
it's an early module observer
并且函数的名称是 start
and the name of the function is start
这只是
and this is just the
粘糊糊的，让我们看看发生了什么
gooey that lets us see what's going
在早期虚拟机内部
on inside of the earlyn vm
和这个系统
and this system
标签只是给我们一些高级信息
tab just gives us some high level information
我们看到我电脑上的核心数量
we see the number of cores on my computer
这里是八核
it's eight cores here
看这里
see over here
我们有非常酷的内存使用情况
we've got the memory usage which is pretty cool
我们有时间
we've got the up time
好吧，这有
well this has
只起床了 1 分钟，因为我们刚刚开始
only been up for 1min because we just started it
我们在这里看到进程数
and we see the number of processes here
它说 98 个进程
it says 98 processes
我们到了，上面写着 83
we're over here it said 83
但那是因为当我们开始
but that's because when we started
观察者本身
the observer itself
它必须启动一些新流程
it had to fire up some new processes
让它做它的工作
to let it do its work
实际查看哪些进程正在运行
to actually see which processes are running
让我们转到进程选项卡
let's go over to the process tab
我们得到了一个完整的细分
and we get a full breakdown of
当前在其早期虚拟机中运行的所有进程
all the processes currently running in their early vm
现在
now
如果您查看这些进程的名称，它们不是
if you look at the name of these processes they're not
可识别为
recognizable as
我们的任何应用程序代码
any of our application code
所以让我们继续按名称排序
so let's go ahead and sort this by name
只需点击此处的名称
just click on name here
我们会再次点击它，它是按字母顺序排列的
and we'll click it again that way it's alphabetical
你会看到所有这些东西都是从elixir dot开始的
and you see all this stuff starting with elixir dot
而早期的长生不老药模块是前缀
while elixir modules in early are prefixed
名为长生不老药点
with the name elixir dot
所以如果我们从顶部开始，我们会看到
and so if we start at the top here we see
有一些相关的东西
there's some stuff related to the
十六进制模块
hex module
我们知道 hex 的 elixir 的包管理器
and we know that hex's elixir's package manager
所以这里有三个进程
so it has three processes here
只是坐在循环中做某事
just sitting in a loop doing something
不确定它到底是什么
not sure exactly what it is
但他们在那里等着什么
but they're waiting on something there
然后我们看到一些相关的流程是
then we see some processes related to is
中间的这个是评估
and this one in the middle is an evaluate
它在一个循环中
and it's sitting in a loop
它有 pid 150
and it has the pid 150
那不应该与我们的性爱会话相匹配
well that shouldn't match our sex session
所以如果我来这里使用 self
so if I come over here and use self
获取当前进程为 pid
to get the current process as pid
果然
well sure enough
我们的会话是 150 以便匹配
our in session is pied 150 so that matches up
就在这儿
right here
然后我们看到一些与elixir的logger相关的进程
then we see some processes related to elixir's logger
有一些与混合本身相关的过程
there's some processes related to mix itself
然后它得到
and then it gets
在这里进入一些erelong函数，如果我们向下滚动
into some erelong functions here and if we scroll down
这里发生了很多事情
there's a bunch of stuff going on here
这是与观察者相关的过程
here's the processes related to the observer
我说当我们点燃粘糊糊的时候
I said when we fired up the gooey
观察者创建了一些流程来完成它的工作
the observer created some processes to do its work
那么这里是那些过程
well here are those processes
事情是这样的
here's the thing
所有长生不老药代码都在一个进程中运行
all elixir code runs in a process
所以要证明
so to demonstrate that
让我们按坑降序排序
let's sort by pit in descending order
然后我们将启动我们的服务器
and then we'll go fire up our server
现在让我们发送一个休眠请求 10 秒
now let's send in a hibernate request for 10 seconds
好的，我们看到了正在进行的过程的坑
okay we see the pit of the process that's working on
现在是 2 点 4 点 39 分 所以如果我们过来
it is two o four thirty nine so if we come over here
就在那里 2 o 4 39 oh
there it is right there two o four thirty nine oh
然后该请求完成
and then that request is done
所以这个过程应该退出
so this process should exit
它将从此列表中删除
and it'll get removed from this list
观察者最酷的地方在于，我们不仅
what's cool about the observer is that we cannot only
看看早期的 vm 发生了什么
see what's going on in the early vm
我们还可以与正在运行的应用程序进行交互
we can also interact with our running application
例如
for example
假设我们有一个流氓流程
let's suppose we have a process that's gone rogue like
让我们冬眠一分钟
let's hibernate for a full minute
好的，这是正在处理的过程 2 2 5 1 3
okay that's process 2 2 5 1 3 that's working on that
那里是 2 2 5 1 3
there it is 2 2 5 1 3
但我们不希望这个过程搞砸了工作
but we don't want this process gumming up the works
所以让我们继续杀了它
so let's go ahead and kill it
我会右击这个
I'll just right click on this
杀死那个进程
kill that process
并且繁荣它消失了
and boom it's gone
正如我们在上一节中看到的
and as we saw in the previous section
请求处理过程是隔离的
the request handling process is isolated
所以杀死它不会使服务器崩溃
so killing it doesn't crash the server
所以如果我来
so if I just come
回到这里
back over here
我只是要控制 c 出来然后我们跑
I'm just going to control c out of that and we run
api很好我们看到我们的服务器仍然响应
api bears well we see that our server still responding
现在
now
当我们从 ix 启动服务器时，服务器代码运行
when we started the server from ix the server code ran
在性过程中
in the sex process
是的，让我们再次找到它
yeah let's find that again
就在这里，这个评估
here it is right here this evaluate
我们看到它正在运行 except 函数
and we see that it's running the except function
正在等待客户端连接
which is waiting for the client connection
因为这就是这里的服务器正在做的事情
because that's what the server over here is doing
这是不专业的
it's inexpert
只是阻止等待该客户端连接
just blocking waiting for that client connection
因为我们是这样运行的
and because we ran it this way
它捆绑了性爱会话
it ties up the sex session
我这里没有提示所以我们不能做
I don't have a prompt right here so we can't do
性方面的其他任何事情
anything else in sex
但我们可以生成服务器
but we could spawn the server
使其同时运行
so that it runs concurrently
在自己的过程中
in its own process
我们知道如何通过调用 spawn 来做到这一点
and we know how to do that by calling spawn
好吧，因为我的性爱时间被捆绑了
all right because my sex session is tied up
我将不得不退出那里
I'm going to have to quit out of there
杀死观察者
that kills the observer
因为我们从观察者开始
because we started observer from
如果我重新开始修复
if I'll start fix up again
所以不要像这样启动我们的服务器
so instead of starting our server like this
我们想在这个bond函数中启动它
we want to start it in this bond function
所以让我们捕获 pid
so let's capture the pid
我们称之为 spawn
we would call spawn
我们可以给它一个匿名函数
and we could give it an anonymous function
这样做
that does this
我们知道这会奏效
and we know that'll work
我们在上一节中看到了
we saw that in the previous section
但要记住
but remember
我们说过你可以用两种不同的方式调用 spawn
we said that you can call spawn in two different ways
使用匿名函数或名称函数
with an anonymous function or with a name function
所以让我们使用一个名称函数
so let's use a name function
为了做到这一点，我们删除了匿名函数
here to do that we drop the anonymous function
spawn 的第一个参数
the first argument to spawn
是模块服务的名称
is the name of the module service
http server 第二个参数的名称是
http server the name of the second argument is then
要运行的功能
the function to run
作为一个原子，所以它将开始
as an atom so it's going to be start
然后第三个参数是参数列表
and then the third parameter is a list of arguments
所以而不是传递一个匿名函数
so instead of passing an anonymous function
我们传递三个参数
we pass it three arguments
模块名称 功能名称
the name of the module the name of the function
然后是列表中的任何参数
and then any arguments in a list
好的
okay
它启动并正在监听连接
and it starts up and it's listening for a connection
但是因为我们在它自己的过程中产生了它
but because we spawn that in its own process
注意我们有一个 ix 提示
notice we have an ix prompt
ix 不再被捆绑
ix isn't tied up anymore
因为我们的服务器运行在一个进程中
because our servers running in a process
使用 pid 154
with the pid one fifty four
所以现在我们可以启动我们的观察者了
so now we can start our observer
我们将转到流程
we'll go over to processes
我要按名称排序
I'm going to sort this by name
我们正在寻找它的性别评估
and we're looking for the sex evaluate there it is
现在我们注意到
and now we notice
当前功能不再接受
that the current function is not accept anymore
它实际上是循环
it's actually loop
因为它在循环等待我们输入一些东西
because it's looping waiting for us to enter something
在六个提示
at the six prompt
但是现在我们有了这个新的进程长生不老药服务器
but now we have this new process elixir server
有 pid 154
has the pid one fifty four
与此处的此 pid 匹配
which matches this pid over here
正如我们所期望的那样，它处于一个接受循环中
and it's sitting in an accept loop as we would expect
所以现在让我们继续发送休眠请求
so now let's go ahead and send that hibernate request
再次
again
我们将休眠 10 秒
we'll hibernate for 10 seconds
回来这里
come back over here
我要按坑排序
I'm going to sort by pit
这将是那里最高的坑
it's going to be the highest pit there it
就在那儿 它正在睡觉 3 2 5 9
is right there it's sleeping 3 2 5 9
和这里的这个一样
which is the same as this one over here
好的，然后它就消失了
all right and then it went away
所以我们看到我们有两个
so we saw that we had two
在观察者中产生进程
spawn processes in the observer
服务器本身和休眠的服务器
both the server itself and the one to hibernate
那么如果我们杀死服务器本身会发生什么
so what happens now if we kill the server itself
只需右键单击
just right click
我们将终止该进程
we'll kill that process
好吧，它消失了
well it goes away
所以如果我们尝试发送一个休眠请求
so if we try to send a request to hibernate
好吧，它无法连接到我们的服务器
well it can't connect to our server
因为服务器死了
because the server is dead
但如果我们来修复它仍然在运行
but if we come up to fix well it's still running
它具有与以往相同的 pid 150
and it has the same pid 150 that it's always had
所以杀死网络服务器并没有杀死性爱会话
so killing the web server didn't kill the sex session
那就对了
that's right
但是如果我们真的终止了性爱会发生什么
but what happens if we do kill the sex session
让我们在这里
let's over here
此评估位于循环坑 150
this evaluate that's sitting in a loop pit 150
让我们杀了它
let's kill it off
嗯，这很有趣
well this is interesting
注意我们最后的六个提示是 6 3
notice our last six prompt was 6 3
它得到了这个 pid 被杀死的出口 pid 150
it got this exit that pid was killed pid 150
现在我们回到 6 1
and now we're back at 6 1
所以它自动重新启动了一个 ix 会话
so it restarted an ix session automatically
事实上，如果我们现在看自我
in fact if we look at self now
不是以前的150
it's not 150 as it was before
现在是 7 6 6 2
it's now 7 6 6 2
所以这是一个具有不同 pid 的全新进程
so it's a brand new process with a different pid
现在它自动重新启动
now it automatically restarted
因为某事
because something
被称为主管正在监视性过程
called a supervisor is monitoring the sex process
主管重新启动谎言
and the supervisor restarts lie
如果它死了，我们稍后会了解有关主管的更多信息
if it dies we'll learn more about supervisors later on
所以我们已经看到一个 Elixir 应用程序是由
so we've seen that an elixir application is made up of
许多孤立的进程同时运行
lots of isolated processes running concurrently
某些
some of the
应用程序启动时自动生成进程
processes are spawned automatically when the app starts
并在应用程序的整个生命周期内继续运行
and continue running for the life of the application
其他进程按需生成
other processes are spawned on demand
现在运行相对较短的时间
and run for a relatively short amount of time now
不同于操作系统进程
unlike operating system processes
长生不老药流程是轻量级的
elixir processes are lightweight and
产卵也快
also fast to spawn
小的
small
应用程序可能正在运行数百个进程
applications might be running hundreds of processes
而更大的应用程序可能正在运行
whereas larger applications might be running
数十万个进程
hundreds of thousands of processes
在高峰时段
during peak times
所有这些
all these
轻量级的 elixir 进程在里面运行
lightweight elixir processes are running inside
一个耳兰虚拟机
of an earland vm
也称为梁
otherwise known as beam
虚拟机本身在单一操作系统中运行
the vm itself runs in a single operating system
当你启动一个 elixir 应用程序时开始的过程
process that started when you start an elixir app
当虚拟机启动时
when the vm starts
它还启动一个调度程序线程
it also starts a scheduler thread
运行谁的工作
whose job it is to run
每个进程当前可以在 cpu 上
each process can currently on the cpu
但同时运行并不意味着
but running concurrently doesn't mean
多个进程运行
that multiple processes run
在同一时间
at exactly the same time
它的工作方式是
the way it works is
调度器分配一段 cpu 时间
that the scheduler allocates a slice of cpu time
对一个过程来说，时间很短
to a process it's a tiny amount of time
时间到了
when the time is up
调度器
the scheduler
准备或暂停正在运行的进程和
preps or suspends the running process and
分配时间
allocates time
到另一个进程
to another process
然后另一个进程轮到它，依此类推
and then another process gets its turn and so on
这样调度器
in this way the scheduler
实际上在进程之间切换如此之快
actually switches between processes so fast
它们似乎同时运行
that they appear to be running simultaneously
将此图视为非常慢动作重播
consider this diagram like a very slow motion replay
这里的结果
the upshot here
是长时间运行的进程不会占用cpu
is that a long running process won't tie up the cpu
每个过程都得到公平的份额
every process gets its fair share
这就是故事的来源
here's where the story gets
更好
even better
您的计算机不太可能只有一个 cpu
it's unlikely that your computer has just one cpu
事实上你在观察者身上看到了粘糊糊的
in fact you saw in the observer gooey
即使是我们老化的笔记本电脑也有多个 cpu 核心
that even our aging laptop has multiple cpu cores
充分利用多核计算机
to take full advantage of multicore computers
虚拟机实际上每创建一个调度程序线程
the vm actually creates one scheduler thread per
cpu核心
cpu core
所以四核计算机将有四个调度程序
so a four core computer will have four schedulers
在每个调度程序中
in each of those schedulers
正在同时运行多个进程
is running multiple processes concurrently
这意味着在任何给定的时间点
which means at any given point in time
四个进程同时运行
four processes are running at exactly the same time
换句话说，它们是并行运行的
in other words they're running in parallel
我们希望这能给您一个赞赏
we hope this gives you an appreciation
对于正在发生的事情
for what's happening
当您调用 spawn 时，在早期的 vm 中
inside the early vm when you call spawn
太不可思议了
it's pretty incredible
vm的方式
the way the vm
负责跨多个调度进程
takes care of scheduling processes across multiple
cpu核心
cpu cores
为了实现并发和并行
as to achieve both concurrency and parallelism
与此同时
all the while
保持应用程序响应新需求
keeping the application responsive to new demands
在下一节中，我们将看到进程如何通信
in the next section we'll see how processes communicate
通过消息
via messages